#xxxxx DON'T DELETE THE FIRST LINE OF THE FILE!
#xxxxx The first character of the first line of this file is a special Unicode
#xxxxx character called the BOM character (0xFEFF), which is invisible to you.
#xxxxx Its presence tells other applications that the entire file is in Unicode.
#
#========== Han-Viet Text Database ============================
#
# @Version: 1
# @Date:    January 17, 2003
# @Contributors:Vuong Doan Nguyen -- levan@hotmail.com
# @Created by Hoc D. Ngo -- hocngo@gmail.com
#      Hoc fixed non Vietnamese letters in the pronunciation column and 
#      converted to this plain text format.
# @DefaultFormatOfValues:
#      (Valid value after colon is hex or just leave it empty)
#
# WinVNKey reads this text file when you ask it to rebuild the Hannom database:
#    Start WinVNKey => click Run button => Select Type Hán Nôm
#    => Han Nom dialog appears
#    => Click the top downward arrow to display a dropdown menu
#    => select menu "Update Han Nom database"
# The rebuild process reads all .txt files in the subdirectories HanViet and NomViet
# and combines them into a single binary file Hannom.dat
# WinVNKey reads Hannom.dat on startup to support Hán Nôm typing.
#
# If you know the syntax of this file, you can add new Hán characters and then
# rebuild the database.  Then restart WinVNKey to use the new database.
#===========================================================
#
# Syntax:
#
# The syntax is very simple:
#      The first column is Unicode values of Hán characters.
#      The second column is the corresponding pronunciation in Latin-based Vietnamese.
#      Each line can have comment that appears after a # sign.
#
#===========================================================
#  How to create an additional Hán-Viet text file?
#
#  Suppose you have found three new Hán characters that are missing from
#  the distribution:
#
#  U+9D1B	uyên
#  U+9D15	đà
#  U+9D12	linh
#
# You want to put them in a separate file to avoid messing up with the
# master database.  
#
# Well, it is better to use Notepad because it will not add invisible characters
# to the file.  Open Notepad, type the three lines as listed above, starting
# with U+.  In other words, you have to omit the leading character # on each line
# and begin with U+ instead.  Then click menu
#        File | Save As
#  Choose:
#        Filename:        Han-Viet-new1  (or any name you want)
#        Save as type:  Text Documents (*.txt)       
#        Encoding:        Unicode
# Then click OK.
#===========================================================
#
#  Syntax Details
#
#  Following are the syntax details if you want to undertand more:
#
# (1) Format of first column:
#         a. Unicode value in hex, say U+99AC, or 0x99AC (i.e., number with prefix U+ or 0x)
#         b. Or Unicode value in decimal, say 19977 (i.e., number without prefix)
#         c. Or True Unicode character like 三 (tam), 車 (xa), 馬 (mã)
#
#     Note when adding new Hán characters to this file:
#        - You can mix these formats, i.e., some rows can be in format (a),
#          some in (b), and others in (c).
#        - A Nôm value of 8300 can be hex or decimal.  If hex, use U+8300.
#          If decimal, use 8300.
#        - If you specify "# @DefaultFormatOfValues: hex"
#          then all numbers without a prefix "U+" or "0x" are hexadecimal.
#        - If you specify "# @DefaultFormatOfValues:" alone,
#          then all numbers without a prefix "U+" or "0x" are decimal.
#        - All numbers with a prefix "U+" or "0x" are ALWAYS hexadecimal,
#          regardless of what you specify for @DefaultFormatOfValues.
#        - For Nôm characters that are double Unicode (surrogate pair), you can list the
#          4 hex digits of the high surrogate followed by the 4 hex digits of the low
#          surrogate.  Or you can list its NCR value.  For example, the Nôm character
#          for "hai" is a surrogate pair:
#                   low surrogate = U+DD29,  high surrogate = U+D840
#          Its HTML (NCR) representation is &#131369; or &#x20129;.
#          Thus you can enter any of the following in the first column for "hai":
#                U+D840DD29 or 0xD840DD29 or 131369 or U+20129 or 0x20129
#
# (2) Format of second column:
#     This column is reserved for pronunciation only. It is separated from the first
#     column by one or more comma, spaces or tabs.
#     If a Nôm character has several pronunciations, you can either list them in the
#     same row separated by commas or put them in separate rows.
#     If you put them in separate rows, make sure the Nôm character in the
#     first column is the same.  NEVER put comment in the second column.
#
# (3) Format of third column:
#     The third column is optional and is used for comment.
#     If you put anything in the third column, put it after a # sign.
#
#     Note that if the second column contains any misspelled Vietnamese word
#     or a foreign word that WinVNKey cannot recognize it as a single Vietnamese
#     word, it will reject this word unless you put "@OK" in the third column.  The
#     presence of "@OK" tells WinVNKey to bypass spelling check.
#
#xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx End of header (don't delete!) xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx
